A Guide to the Joseph D. Eggleston Collection, 1896-1949 (Bulk 1905-1920)
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Joseph D. Eggleston Collection, 1896-1949, n.d. (Bulk 1905-1920)
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2009-128
0.3 cu. ft. 1 box
The collection contains publications and pamphlets authored by or including articles authored by and about Joseph D. Eggleston. Materials relate Eggleston's tenure with VPI and Hampden-Sydney College, as well as local religious and social causes. Several of the articles contain Eggleston's marginalia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Joseph D. Eggleston Collection was purchased by Special Collections in September 2009. An additional group of similar publications was purchased by Special Collections in March 2010 and a third group in December 2011.
Biographical Information
Joseph D. Eggleston was born in Prince Edward County, Virginia, in 1867. He attended college at Hampden-Sydney College, completing his degree in 1886. He taught at schools in several southern states before becoming the superintendent in Asheville, North Carolina in 1891 and later superintendent of schools in Farmville, Virginia. During his tenure as state Superintendent of Public Instruction (1906-1912), he worked hard for improvements in rural schools. In January of 1913, he began work with the Field Service in Rural Education in the US Office of Education. The same year, he resigned to take the post of VPI President (1913-1919). In 1919, Eggleston left VPI for the Presidency of his alma mater, Hampden-Sydney College. He served there from 1919 to 1939. Eggleston died in Farmville, Virginia, in 1953.
For more information on Joseph D. Eggleston and his administration at VPI, see:
Records of Joseph Dupuy Eggleston, President, Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1913-1919. RG 2/7. Finding aid available on the Virginia Heritage database.
Kinnear, Duncan Lyle. The First 100 Years; A History of Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Blacksburg: Virginia Polytechnic Institute Educational Foundation, 1972.
Scope and Content
The collection contains publications and pamphlets authored by or including articles authored by and about Joseph D. Eggleston. Materials relate to Eggleston's tenure at VPI and Hampden-Sydney College, as well as religious and other education organizations. Several of the articles contain Eggleston's marginalia. Examples include opinion pieces for the YMCA publication Rural Manhood (1917), articles about Eggleston for the Bulletin of Hampden-Sydney College (1917-1918), and an address to the Virginia State Teachers' Association (1910).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically. Undated material is at the end.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Records of Joseph Dupuy Eggleston, President, Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1913-1919. RG 2/7. Finding aid available on the Virginia Heritage database. Please note: These presidential records are in storage and require 1-2 days notice for retrieval.
Index Terms
Persons:
Eggleston, J. D., (Joseph Dupuy), 1867-1953
Subjects:
Faculty; Hampden-Sydney College; University Archives; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Contents List
- Age of Consent Legislation, March 24, 1896. (Box-folder 1:1)
- "Announcement to the People of Virginia," 1905. (Box-folder 1:1)
- "Appointment of Division Superintendents Under the New Law—A Plea for Co-operation," February 1909. (Box-folder 1:1)
- "Extension Work in Virginia-Its Possibilities and Needs," August 10, 1909. (Box-folder 1:1)
- "Dust and Diseases: One Way to Stop Them," November 3, 1909. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Fifth Annual Conference Handbook: Virginia Educational Conference, November 22-25, 1910. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Annual Report of the Co-Operative Eduation Association of Virginia for the Year Ending November 20, 1911. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Virginia State Teachers' Association Annual Proceedings, 1910-1911. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Sanitary Survey of the Schools of Orange County, VA, 1914. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Counting the Cost, 1915. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Extension Bulletin, No. 2. Annual Report. Farmers' Co-Operative Demonstration and Extension Work for 1914, July 1915. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Extension Bulletin, No. 4. Annual Report. Farmers' Co-Operative Demonstration and Extension Work for 1915, January 1916. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Rural Manhood, vol. VIII, no. 1, 1917. (Box-folder 1:2)
- "First Aid to Country Teacher," address delivered April 11, 1917. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Rural Manhood, vol. IX, no. 6, 1918. (2 copies) (Box-folder 1:2)
- Bulletin of Hampden-Sydney College, vol. XIV, no. 2, 1919. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Hampden-Sydney Magazine, vol. XXXVI, no. 3, 1919. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Bulletin of Hampden-Sydney College, vol. XIV, no. 3, 1919. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Hampden-Sidney, Our Denominational College: Its Value and Purpose. Report of President J. D. Eggleston to the Synod of Virginia, November 11, 1920. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Second Presbyterian Church bulletin, Petersburg, Virginia, 1920. (Box-folder 1:3)
- "The Pilot," (Published Weekly by the First Baptist Church, Logan, West Virginia, February 21, 1921. (Box-folder 1:3)
- American Education, vol. XXIV, no. 7, 1921. (Box-folder 1:3)
- "The One Book for Everyone," 1931. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Great Scientists Who Were Christians, 1937. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Extension Work in Virginia, A Brief History, 1907-1940. (Box-folder 1:3)
- "Glimpses of the Past: Correspondence of Robert Campbell, 1834-1845," Missouri Historical Society, v.VIII, no. 1-6, January - June 1941. (Box-folder 1:3)
- "Historic Slate Hill Plantation in Virgina," 1945. (Box-folder 1:3)
- "Sources of Historical Data on Hampden-Sydney and Southern Virginia," 1949. (Box-folder 1:3)
- "Chairs for Teachers" pamphlet, n.d. (2 copies) (Box-folder 1:3)
- "An Announcement" pamphlet on Hampden-Sydney College, n.d. (Box-folder 1:3)
- "The Church Building and Home Mission Fund" pamphlet, n.d. (Box-folder 1:3)
- "Travelling Libraries" and "A Word About School Libraries," n.d. (Box-folder 1:3)